<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="6"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[COMMISSION ON POPULATION AND

  DEVELOPMENT (POPCOM)


  FAMILY WELLNESS CLINIC-ASC’s


  MOST FREQUENT QUESTIONS ASKED BY


  FAMILY PLANNING CLIENTS DURING THE

  COVID-19 PANDEMIC



























                                                                                        When in doubt


                                                                                        call


                                                                                        09175970770/



                                                                                        09988652810/



                                                                                        09189234912/



                                                                                        8531-6897



                                                                                        8782-9284]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Is contraception/family planning safe to use during the covid-19

         pandemic?



         Yes. All modern methods of contraception are safe to use, including during the COVID-19 pandemic.

         If you have had a baby in the last six months or have a health condition, such as diabetes, high blood

         pressure, or breast cancer – or if you smoke – seek advice from a health care professional to ensure
         you are using a method of contraception which is suitable and safe for you.


         I want to avoid getting pregnant during the covid-19 pandemic. What
         can I do?

         If  you do  not  want  to  become  pregnant,  you  should start or  continue  to  use  your

         contraceptive method of choice. You may be able to access information and contraceptive services from
         a healthcare provider by phone or online.

         If you cannot access these services you may opt for a method that is available without a prescription
         (such     as     condoms, spermicides,           diaphragm, pills, or     emergency       contraceptive
         pills) from a nearby pharmacy or drug shop.


         I can’t access my contraceptive method of choice what do you advise?



         If you cannot access your contraceptive method of choice – perhaps because it requires a prescription,

         or because it can only be given to you by a health worker – consider using condoms, fertility awareness-
         based methods, lactational amenorrhea (if you are exclusively breastfeeding), or other contraceptive
         methods that are recommended for self-care in your country.



         What is the best contraceptive method to use during the covid-19

         pandemic?


         All modern methods of contraception help to prevent pregnancy. Women and their partners can choose
         any  modern  contraceptive  method  that  is  acceptable  to  and  safe  for  them.  The  best  method  of
         contraception is the one that works well for you.]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Condoms, when they are used consistently and correctly, are the only method of contraception that

         help to prevent unintended pregnancy and protect against sexually transmitted infections, including
          HIV.  They can be used together with other methods of contraception to protect against both

         unintended pregnancy and sexually transmitted infections.


          Emergency contraceptive pills can prevent up to 95% of pregnancies when taken within 5 days after
          intercourse, and they can be taken by anyone with or without a health condition.




          I want to change my contraceptive method. Is this possible?


          Yes. It may be difficult however, to access all the methods of contraception that are normally available in your

         country due to restrictions on movement, lack of supply, as well as increased demands on health providers
          and services.


         If you have a pre-existing health condition, consult a provider to find out what options suit you best, and which




          are   available   and feasible. Seek advice and   information from       your   health provider and consider



        using methods  that  do  not  have medical restrictions  like minipills, condoms,  fertility  awareness-based

        methods, diaphragm, spermicides or lactational amenorrhea if you are exclusively breastfeeding.





        I want to remove or replace my implant or IUD, can I do this during covid-

        19 pandemic?


        Removal of long acting methods such as implants or IUDs, after the recommended period of use (and routine

        follow  up  appointments) may  not  be  prior   itized  by  your  country’s  health  system  during  this  health

        emergency. Seek advice from your health provider.


          If, due to restrictions on movement due to the COVID-19 pandemic you cannot have your long acting method




        removed straight away, it is important to use another method of contraception to avoid pregnancy at this

        time.


        There are no medical problems caused by delaying removal of long acting methods such as implants or


        IUDs. Do not try to remove the contraception method yourself; wait until you are able to access health care

        from a trained provider.]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Why is providing contraception/family planning as well as family
          planning services and information important during the covid-19

          pandemic?


          Contraception  and  family  planning  information  and  services are life-saving  and important
           at all times. Sexual activity does not cease with the COVID-19 pandemic, it is therefore crucial to ensure

          that people are able to access rights-based services and information to initiate and / or continue use of

          contraception.


          By preventing unintended pregnancies, contraception helps to protect girls and women from the negative
          health consequences of unintended pregnancies, which can save their lives. Contraception reduces the

          need for abortion, meaning that women and girls are less at risk of unsafe abortion, which again can be

           lifesaving.


           Condoms,  when  used  consistently  and  correctly,  help  to  prevent  both  unintended  pregnancies  and
          sexually transmitted infections (including STIs).

          In addition, by preventing the negative health consequences associated with unintended pregnancies,
          unsafe  abortion and  sexually  transmitted  infections  (including  HIV),  contraception  can  help  alleviate

          unnecessary additional pressure on already-stretched health systems which are working hard to address

          COVID-19.]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[09175970770 / 09988652810 / 09189234912 / 87829284]]></page></pages></Search>
